<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-04T21:31:09+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alex Lee</title><subtitle>Drupal developer. Marxist political economist. Digital critic. Yorkshire, now Manchester.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Notes on Travelling on the Lübeck - Malmö Ferry</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal/2019/03/01/lubeck-malmo-ferry-marx-harvey-capital.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Travelling on the Lübeck - Malmö Ferry" /><published>2019-03-01T20:00:54+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-01T20:00:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal/2019/03/01/lubeck-malmo-ferry-marx-harvey-capital</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal/2019/03/01/lubeck-malmo-ferry-marx-harvey-capital.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is a bit of an experiment: partly holiday blog and partly a bunch of random thoughts about political economy. I don’t know whether it will work, but lets see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bus from Lübeck dropped me off at the corner of Skandanaviankai and Skandanavianallee. I was about to go on a journey… yes, that’s it. Scandanavia. I could see the ferry terminal down the road, but it had numerous signs saying no pedestrians, giving me the impression that to walk down this road was to be crushed by a big truck. But seeing no alternative pedestrian route, I walked it anyway. I walked through a barren road, filled with weeds, tarmac, and piles of containers destined for who-knows-where. The road widened and directed vehicles to get into the right lane. I followed signs to Malmö, and walked through corridors through parked trucks. Barriers appeared in front of me, where passengers would get their passport checked, and saw a woman in a fluorescent jacket behind a railing. “Excuse me!” I asked, “How do I get to the passenger terminal?” “Oh, hello Mr. Lee! Just take a walk up those stairs by the barrier, and cross over the bridge. I’ll be over in a minute.” “Thanks!” I said. Wait. What? How did this woman know who I was? As I walked, I wondered whether this was a Kafka novel, where all manner of confusing signs had been placed in front of me, simply for the purpose of confusing &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;, whether I was somehow expected to be lost in this ferry port. I went over the bridge and waited in the reception. The woman, I found out was called Olga, and knew my name because I was the only foot passenger on her list today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you do, I was starting on Marx’s Capital Vol II on this holiday. While Vol I has been recognised as a literary classic, Vol II was unfinished, unappreciated and ignored. There are some good reasons for this. It is dry, confusing, and has little of the fantastic literary style of Vol I. David Harvey does a great job in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/42904803-a-companion-to-marx-s-capital&quot;&gt;A Companion To Marx’s Capital: The Complete Edition&lt;/a&gt; of explaining this, but also describes how ignoring Vol II has left a massive gap in the theory. Harvey’s later work explains how capitalism constantly reshapes the environment. Natural land is built on, farmed, modified; industries built up; roads and transport constructed; then new technology appears, and these industries are abandoned. Capitalism constantly changes our landscapes and cities as businesses compete to build new technology and gain competitive advantage, while old infrastructure is worthless and left to rot and rust. We can see this in the way that major ports in the UK lie abandoned; while massive airports have emerged in our cities instead. Our urban environment is always in flux in capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ferry terminal at Travemund was an example of this. In the past, ferries were very popular ways to travel. Before low-cost air travel, ferries were the way many people would travel. Even in the 90s, they were still popular, and I used to take the ferry to Esbjerg in Denmark most years with my family. But these passenger ferries no longer run, unable to compete with modern air travel. The last one from Newcastle to Denmark left in 2014. I still have good memories of these journeys. I loved the little cabins with portholes looking out to sea, standing on deck and watching the waves, and of course, the 90s arcade machines with games like R-Type. (Speaking of old technologies, the 90s arcades with controls consisting of no more than a joystick and a couple of buttons to bash at 20p a go were &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much better than new modern ones! An I’m not just saying in because I’m a grump.). However, these sentimental attachments to modes of travel mean little in a world driven by technological innovation, merciless competition, and profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the present, and on the deck of the ferry to Malmo, I had a good view of the port. The space around port had probably been incredibly diverse in wildlife before this port was built, an environment where marsh and reeds were common, where silt piled up next to the banks, and where sea and fresh water merged. All this was gone on this port now: it was covered in tarmac. I could see a clear footpath, the path I should have taken to get to the terminal, but it seemed like there were no signs anymore. I guess so few foot passengers got the bus that they didn’t bother with signs now. It may have been a common passenger terminal in the past, but now my field of view was covered in frieght containers, like a sort-of industrial-scale Legoland. Diggers churned up the remaining soil I could see. Even though I most of my vision was of tarmac and containers, evidently, this wasn’t enough space. Capitalism demands constantly growing economy: more stuff sent to more places for more people to spend and consume. The passengers on the ship had changed too. Rather than families and holiday-makers like I used to see on the ferries, everyone else on this ship appeared to be a truck driver. As well as changing the built environment, capitalism changes demographics too; the people that took this ferry were different demographic section to the ones I shared ferries with when I was younger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t particularly romantic, but I still had my sentimental attachment to sea-travel, and I greatly enjoyed the journey. I focused on reading. In everyday life, I don’t often focus on reading for long periods, without getting distracted, but here I was forced to, which was challenging but eventually very enjoyable. The ferry lasted about ten hours. Some of the time I just watched the sea, and eventually I got a fantastic sunset to watch. Before docking in Malmo, I even got to go right under the famous bridge from Denmark to Sweden. Finally, I got to meet Liz after her own trip to Sweden. Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism demands that everything be measure by price. But we can understand our sentimental attachments to things part of what Marx calls the “use-value” of things we buy. In capitalism, the price, or the “exchange-value” is everything. Considered in this way, of course people will fly instead of taking the ferry, you get from A to B much faster and possibly cheaper too; we are told there is no stopping this change of technologies, so accept that planes will replace ferry travel and move on. Capitalism would like people to have no personal attachment to products, and merely to behave as rational and logical calculating machines, we will always have feelings towards the world around us. Having an emotional attachment to our world is part of being alive, but the capitalist system can only see prices, efficiency, profit. Marx rejects this, and insists we focus on “use-value”, which includes the purpose and connection to our world, not simply a price. The “use-value” of ferry travel for me is the time it gives me to read, a feeling of calm as waves rock the ship, and time I have to sit and watch the sea. Focusing on “use-value” rather than the price leads us to conclude that profit and efficiency should not demand cheaper and faster travel. It should also be travel that enables us to connect to the world, and improves our relationships and our lives. We should aim to build genuine emotional connections to the world when we travel, because we are emotional beings. We are not capitalist automatons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on this trip, I got the ferry overnight from Holland to Harwich, and similarly, I enjoyed this experience greatly. But these sentimental attachments to travel don’t mean much in a profit-driven world, and I imagine ferries will continue to decline. Even though we are regularly told that change is inevitable, the particular technological changes we see in today’s society are not necessary. They are only required because competition demands new and more efficient technologies. We are told there is nothing we can do to stop new technologies from usurping old ones, and no point in hanging onto the past. This is wrong. Our personal attachment to forms of travel we enjoy is essential.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel," /><category term="marx" /><summary type="html">This post is a bit of an experiment: partly holiday blog and partly a bunch of random thoughts about political economy. I don’t know whether it will work, but lets see.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Social Value?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/economics/2019/02/10/unite-nw-389-social-value-manchester.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Social Value?" /><published>2019-02-10T20:00:54+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-10T20:00:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/economics/2019/02/10/unite-nw-389-social-value-manchester</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/economics/2019/02/10/unite-nw-389-social-value-manchester.html">&lt;p&gt;Social value… what is it? There are different conceptions of this, but it is best explained with an example, which was how Nigel Rose from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.manchestercommunitycentral.org/&quot;&gt;MACC&lt;/a&gt; started to explain the concept in a talk at the February branch meeting of  &lt;a href=&quot;https://unite-nw389.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Unite NW389&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A restaurant, for example, could consider social value as perhaps supporting and donating to charities. Starbucks has its own charity, Starbucks Foundation, so when you buy a coffee there, some of your money goes towards this supporting communities. Some supermarkets will advertise what local charities they donate to on a noticeboard, for example, supporting local sports teams. Supermarkets providing places for food banks to collect for local people is a bit better, but still, is not the solution. However, Nigel Rose argued that this is not an effective way to generate social value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real social value must be an integral part of the organisation. Instead of making donations to charity, a local restaurant could consider how its own core functions of business could benefit local people. We know that zero-hour contracts have a damaging effect on employees, creating anxiety, financial insecurity, and place people’s ability to function on the whims of an unpredictable market. These contracts contribute to homelessness, debt, and poor mental health. So a restaurant could begin its quest to increase social value by banning these contracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other ways to create social value could be actively campaign against zero-hour contracts, creating high standards of health and safety, encouraging trade unions, and providing more breaks for staff. One restaurant recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/food/2018/oct/24/the-chefs-who-are-closing-for-dinner-to-pursue-a-healthier-life&quot;&gt;decided to close for staff evening meals&lt;/a&gt;, because restaurant staff often end up working horrendously long shifts without providing the minimum  break time for staff. A restaurant could also encourage staff to apply from disadvantaged backgrounds, try to reduce food waste,  source food locally, and even consider alternative methods of ownership, such as cooperative worker-owned model, where every worker has a democratic say over the businesses. This is genuine social value, where the core function of the businesses caring for employees, society and our environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of social value as simply a donation to charity, an add-on to the core function of the business is an idea that fails under examination. For many businesses, the desire to improve society, especially in the age of austerity, is a genuine one. People can see the social problems we have and want to help. But a business that donates to charity to help is not doing enough – organisations needs to look how its own business functions are contributing to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, we can examine Tesco’s supermarket. Holding food banks at Tesco’s is helping some people to have access to food in a country impoverished by Tory austerity. This is genuinely making a difference to many people in the country. However, Tescos core business contributes to the problem: the excellent and well-researched book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.waterstones.com/book/tescopoly/andrew-simms/9781845295110&quot;&gt;Tescopoply&lt;/a&gt; shows how new Tescos stores have a net negative impact on jobs on a local region. Although Tesco creates jobs, more jobs are lost by local businesses closing after a Tesco opens. Additionally, Tesco increasingly replaces workers with automatic checkouts, and so on. Workers are often given zero hours contracts, which creats massive insecurity and reports show that people can end up taking home &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mirror.co.uk/news/uk-news/argos-homebase-tesco-exploit-workers-3630972&quot;&gt;only £19 per week&lt;/a&gt;. Donations to a food bank do not absolve the supermarket of the fact that they are part of the problem by making workers redundant, providing insecure contracts, and damaging the local economy. Tesco is overall having a negative impact on social cohesion, and the fact that they support local food banks does not absolve them of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel Rose explained how this relates to Manchester. Manchester City Council are very keen on supporting social value – the staff there can see the terrible effect that austerity is having on their services and the people in the area, and so council has encouraged businesses to support social issues. This means that local businesses make connections to social causes in the area, for example, connecting to local charities and voluntary organisations, and providing donations. Construction companies are particularly keen on this concept of social value. It means that social value is easy to measure – donations and spending on projects that are good for local people can be accounted for, measured, and even used for promotion and marketing. However, these construction companies do not look at how the core functions of the business create the problem. Many of the new high rise flats in Manchester are bought by investors that are not interested in living in them, they are tools for accumulating private profit, not for providing homes. These construction companies could effectively try to address the problem of homelessness by providing &lt;a href=&quot;https://labour.org.uk/issues/housing-for-the-many/&quot;&gt;genuinely affordable housing&lt;/a&gt; for people on low incomes, by putting limits on buy-to-let landlords, and limiting overseas purchases of housing, which are issues pushing people towards homelessness. Making donations to charities to support homeless people doesn’t erase the fact that construction companies are part of the problem in Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our branch, &lt;a href=&quot;https://unite-nw389.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Unite NW389&lt;/a&gt;, supports Nigel Rose’s work on changing Manchester Council’s approach to social value. This means that social value should not be an addon, it must be integrated into the organisation, showing respect for workers, communities and our environment across Manchester. A solution has to put social value above profits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Social value… what is it? There are different conceptions of this, but it is best explained with an example, which was how Nigel Rose from MACC started to explain the concept in a talk at the February branch meeting of Unite NW389.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MA Dissertation: an Ideology Critique of the Cambridge Analytica Scandal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/politics/2018/12/05/californian-ideology-cambridge-analytica.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MA Dissertation: an Ideology Critique of the Cambridge Analytica Scandal" /><published>2018-12-05T15:14:54+00:00</published><updated>2018-12-05T15:14:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/politics/2018/12/05/californian-ideology-cambridge-analytica</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/politics/2018/12/05/californian-ideology-cambridge-analytica.html">&lt;p&gt;In Decembder 2018 I submitted my dissertation on ideology and the Cambridge Analytica scandal. It examines how ideology functions in Silicon Valley, specifically examining Facebook and how the condradictions of this ideology emerged in the Cambridge Analytica scandal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is available to read here: &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/documents/cambridge-analytica-californian-ideology.pdf&quot;&gt;The Californian Ideology &amp;amp; Analysing the Cambridge Analytica Scandal.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An epub version for e-readers is available too - &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/documents/cambridge-analytica-californian-ideology.epub&quot;&gt;The Californian Ideology &amp;amp; Analysing the Cambridge Analytica Scandal.epub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pleased to get awarded 74% for this dissertation, which just pushed me into getting a distinction overall. A few of the comments from my tutors are worth noting. In the dissertation I use the term “transference” to describe how the Californian Ideologue shifts the logic of capitalism onto technology through a belief in techno-determinism. However, “displacement” would be a more accurate psychoanalytic term. The other point to note is that I use the concept of “the Real” to show how Facebook were terrified of the revelations in the Cambridge Analytica scandal may destroy their “reality”, and therefore tried to avoid this confrontation. However, “the Real” is not necessarily a negative or terrifying encounter - it can also be an awe-inspiring positive experience, but one that we cannot comprehend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to my tutors Greig Charnock and Japhy Wilson at the University of Manchester for supporting me through this. Doing the MA in Political Economy was one of the best decisions I have made, and this MA would be great for anyone interested in critical examination of political economy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In Decembder 2018 I submitted my dissertation on ideology and the Cambridge Analytica scandal. It examines how ideology functions in Silicon Valley, specifically examining Facebook and how the condradictions of this ideology emerged in the Cambridge Analytica scandal.</summary></entry></feed>